Religion Collection, 1734-1997 (bulk 1800-1950)
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Religion collection
1734-1997
1800-1950
MS 448
10 boxes (7.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
This collection is comprised of bibliographies, articles, pamphlets, biographies, newspaper clippings and tracts all pertaining to women's roles within religion and the church. Included are two volumes of The Woman's Bible (1897); a tract entitled "Account of Abigail Hutchinson: a young woman hopefully converted at Northampton, Mass (1734);" pamphlets and articles on the education and training of missionaries and historical sketches of missionary societies; matriarchal religions and founders of independent and separatist church movements; and documentation on women's organizations and caucuses from various religious sects.
The collection is comprised of bibliographies, articles, pamphlets, biographies, newspaper clippings, and tracts all pertaining to women's roles within religion and the church. Dating from 1734 to 1979, the bulk of the materials are dated after 1800. Included are two volumes of The Woman's Bible (1897); a tract entitled "Account of Abigail Hutchinson: a young woman hopefully converted at Northampton, Mass" (1734); pamphlets, articles and other materials on the education and training of missionaries and historical sketches of missionary societies, matriarchal religions, founders of independent and separatist church movements, and women's organizations and caucuses from various religious sects. There are also biographical files on individual women religious thinkers and leaders and an oral history of Patricia Page (Smith College, class of 1944), done for the Episcopal Women's History Project (1997).
This collection is organized into six series:
I. General
II. Individuals
III. Clergy
IV. Organizations
V. Missionary Work
VI. Sects
Oversize materials
Books on Shelf
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions are expected.
History of the Collection
Materials in this subject collection were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors. One donor to this collection, Patricia Page, was Smith College Class of 1944.
Search Terms
England--Church history--Sources; Feminist spirituality; Missionaries-- History--Sources; Spouses of clergy-- History--Sources; United States--Church history--Sources; Women--Religion--History--Sources; Women clergy--United States--History--Sources; Women in Christianity--History--Sources; Women in church work--Catholic Church; Women missionaries--History--Sources; Sophia Smith Collection
- SERIES I. GENERAL
  - Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bibliographies 1971-80, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Women in the Bible: articles, pamphlets, notes, and miscellaneous 1922-80, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Woman's Bible, 2 volumes: Vol. I, The Pentateuch 1897; Vol. II, Judges, Kings, Prophets and Apostles1898; article1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Women in the Church: articles 1914-71, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Women in the Church, pamphlets and booklets [one in French] 1734, 1868, 1903-71, undated (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Matriarchal Religions: Pesek-Marous, Eduard. Salvatore, Bull of Salvation (Tau Press, California: 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Research Papers
    - Susan Milson, "Women and the Medieval Church" 1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Nancy Schwartz. "Women as Leaders and Founders of Independent and Separatist Church Movements in Sub-Saharan Africa" 1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Periodicals
    - CommonwealMay 15, 1970; Dec. 24, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Daughters of SarahNov. 1974, Jan. 1975, Mar. 1977, May 1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Inward LightSummer/Fall, 1964; Spring, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Kairos, an independent quarterly of liberal religionSpring 1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Post AmericanAugust/September, 1974 [Evangelical Feminism] (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Women's Caucus-Religious Studies NewsletterMarch 1973, Fall 1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - The Student World, Third Quarter 1936 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- SERIES II. INDIVIDUALS
  - Collected biographies 1921, 1974, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Praise Book (songs) 1877 (Box 3)
  - Antoinette Brown Blackwell: photographs and article 1914, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Olympia Brown: pamphlets, articles, autobiography, letters 1915-63 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Mary Daly: 3 articles written by Daly 1971-72 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Mary Dyer: articles 1959 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Mary Baker Eddy: articles 1910-70, undated, [see also OVERSIZE MATERIAL] (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Julia A.J. Foote: autobiography 1879 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Elizabeth Fry: articles, photographs, and letters 1925, 1936, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Barbara Heck: pamphlets and articles 1927-33, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Joan of Arc, [see Books on shelf] (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Ruth Anna Lindley: biography 1893 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Aimee Semple McPherson: biography and articles 1926-33, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Madalyn Murray O'Hair: pamphlets 1966, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 28a)
  - Patricia Page [See next box] (Box 3)
  - Mary Rotch: biography 1956 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Agnes Maude Royden
    - Pamphlets, articles, letter written by Royden 1915-43, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Articles about Royden 1922-64, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Elizabeth Ann Seton: biography and article 1921, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Joanna Southcott: article 1946 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Augusta E. Stetson: letters 1904, 1914, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Patricia Page: oral history transcript and audiocassette tapes (4)1997 (Box 3a, Folder 34a)
- SERIES III. CLERGY
  - Pamphlets 1892-63, undated (Box 3b, Folder 35)
  - Articles 1891-38 (Box 3b, Folder 36)
  - International Association of Women Ministers: pamphlet and poster 1982 (Box 3b, Folder 37)
  - International Association of Women Preachers: constitution and letter 1919, 1924 (Box 3b, Folder 38)
  - Society for the Equal Ministry of Men and Women in the Church: pamphlets 1929-47, undated (Box 3b, Folder 39)
  - Minister's wives: articles 1923-37, undated (Box 3b, Folder 40)
- SERIES IV. ORGANIZATIONS
  - Campus Ministry Women: newslettersApril 1974-May 1982 (Box 4, Folder 40a)
  - Center for Women and Religion: pamphlets and letter 1981 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Ecumenical Women's Center: Personnel handbook and newsletters 1974-82 (Box 4, Folder 41a)
  - Ethical Culture Society (Clara Babcock Bisbee): article and pamphlet 1892, undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Evangelical Women's Caucus: pamphlet and letter 1975 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America: questionnaires, pamphlets, reports, and newsletter 1925-49 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Interracial Conference of Church Women (Federal Council of Churches): articles and pamphlets 1926-29, undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Massachusetts Council of Churches. Task Force on Women: press release, article, and newsletter 1974, undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Miscellaneous: articles and pamphlets 1864, 1922-38, undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - National Council of Churches. United Church Women: booklets, study guide,and articles 1959, 1970, undated (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - National Organization for Women: Task Force on Women and Religion: reports, mission statement 1973, undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Philadelphia Task Force on Women in Religion: newslettersMarch/April 1973-March/April 1974 (Box 4, Folder 49a)
  - The Woman's Church (New York City): announcement 1879 (Box 4, Folder 49b)
  - Women's Centennial Congress. Commission on Ethical and Religious Values: preparatory material 1940 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Women's Center for Theologizing: reports, programs, resources, retreats, and training materials 1974-1976, undated (Box 4, Folder 50a)
  - Women's Ordination Conference: letter and donation information 1994 (Box 4, Folder 50b)
  - World Council of Churches: pamphlets, booklets, reports, lectures, letter, and bibliography 1947-64 (Box 4, Folder 51)
- SERIES V. MISSIONARY WORK
  - Missionaries
    - Articles and pamphlets 1900-31, undated (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Education and training: booklets 1913-44, undated (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Missionaries in Asia
      - General: letters and articles 1929-40 (Box 5, Folder 54)
      - Kiangsi 1919 & Foochow 1913 Women's conferences (Box 5)
      - Montgomery, Helen Barrett. Western Women in Eastern Lands (New York: MacMillan Company 1911 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous biography: articles and pamphlets 1917-30 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Loanza Goulding Benton (1822-99): biography, diary (1847-51), recollections, article, photographs, and drawings (all in one typed compellation) 1847-1869, undated (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Seraphina Haynes Everett (1823-55): diary (typed copy)March 3, 1845- April 17, 1845 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Frances Cousens Gage: biography 1918 (Box 5, Folder 57a)
    - Florence Hooper (1789-1826): booklet, material by Hooper, bibliography1957, undated (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Ann Hasseltine Judson (1819-1903): letter1826 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Rebecca Toy Lore (1793-1812): diarySeptember 17, 1847-December 6, 1847 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - Harriet Atwood Newell (1874-1939): bookundated (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - Genevieve Davis Olds: remembrance and photograph 1939, undated (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Rhoda Orme (1842-1933): reports1954, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Clara Gray Schauffler (1982-1955): biographyundated (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Ruth Isabel Seabury: biography, Part 2 of 21955 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Missionary societies
    - Birdsnest Foundation: booklet and pamphlets 1930-37, undated (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - Board of Foreign Missions of the Presbyterian Church: pamphlets, articles, and letter 1900-52 (Box 6, Folder 67)
    - Council of Women for Home Missions: articles 1923-31 (Box 6, Folder 68)
    - East London Institute for Home and Foreign Missions: book 1887 (Box 6, Folder 69)
    - Federation of Woman's Boards of Foreign Missions of North America: reports and minutes 1926-28 (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - Female Cent Institution (Aux. to the New Hampshire Missionary Society): report 1888 (Box 6, Folder 70a)
    - Female Missionary Society for the Poor of the City of New York: report 1817 (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Foreign Missions Conference, Committee on Women's Work: report and minutes 1939 (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - International Missionary Council: article and booklets 1927-28, undated (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - The King's Daughters Settlement: report, article, and periodical 1896-1928 (Box 6, Folder 74)
    - Presbyterian Women's Home Missions: reports, financial information, and drafts of resolutions 1877-78 (Box 6, Folder 74a)
    - Trinity Church Association and Trinity Mission House: booklet 1956 (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - United Study of Missions: bookletsundated (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - Women's Board of Missions: pamphlets, letter, booklets, article, and reports 1882-1925, undated (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - Women's Board of Missions for the Pacific Islands: reports 1874-84 (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - Women's Foreign Missionary Society: articles 1871-1931, undated (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - Woman's Home Missionary Society: reports and articles 1893-1930 (Box 6, Folder 80)
    - Women's Presbyterian Board of Missions of the North West: booklet and periodicals 1882-1911 (Box 6a, Folder 81)
    - Women's Baptist Missionary Society, Women's American Baptist Home Mission Society, and American Baptist Foreign Mission Society: booklets and article 1881-1927, undated (Box 6a, Folder 82)
    - L.H. Daggett. Historical Sketches of Women's Missionary Societies in America and England, Boston 1883 (Box 6a)
- SERIES VI. SECTS
  - Anglican
    - General: booklets and articles 1908-43, undated (Box 7, Folder 83)
    - Anglican Group for the Ordination of Women: booklets, reports 1930-39, undated (Box 7, Folder 84)
    - Clergy: booklets and articles 1917-58, undated (Box 7, Folder 85)
    - Deaconesses: booklets and articles 1912-48, undated (Box 7, Folder 86)
    - League of the Church Militant: pamphlets 1919-28, undated (Box 7, Folder 87)
  - Baptist: articles 1923-32, undated (Box 7, Folder 88)
  - Catholic
    - General: biographies (one in German), pamphlets, and articles 1912-45, undated (Box 7, Folder 89)
    - National Council of Catholic Women: booklets and articles 1921-52, undated (Box 7, Folder 90)
    - Sisterhoods: articles and biographies 1922-69, undated (Box 7, Folder 91)
    - Women's Ordination Conference: pamphlets and booklet of programs 1979-82, undated (Box 7, Folder 92)
  - Church of Scotland: articles and booklets 1912-47, undated (Box 8, Folder 93)
  - Congregational: articles and pamphlets 1929-50, undated (Box 8, Folder 94)
  - Doukhobors: articles 1959 (Box 8, Folder 95)
  - Islam: booklets and articles 1881-1933, undated (Box 8, Folder 96)
  - Judaism: books, articles, and periodicals 1924-84, undated (Box 8, Folder 97)
  - Lutheran: articles 1925-28, undated (Box 8, Folder 98)
  - Methodist
    - General: articles and programs 1920-74, undated (Box 8, Folder 99)
    - Clergy: articles 1922-33 (Box 8, Folder 100)
    - Deaconesses: booklets and articles 1922-63, undated (Box 8, Folder 101)
    - United Methodist Women's Caucus: newsletter (The Yellow Ribbon)March 1973-Fall 1977, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 101a)
  - Mormon: booklets, article, and letter 1884-1979, undated (Box 9, Folder 102)
  - Presbyterian
    - General: articles 1921-28 (Box 9, Folder 103)
    - Clergy: articles 1925-58 (Box 9, Folder 104)
  - Protestant Episcopal
    - General: booklets, articles 1919-74, undated (Box 9, Folder 105)
    - Sisterhood: book, booklets, and periodicals 1879-1963, undated (Box 9, Folder 106)
  - Reformed Church of America, clergy: article 1927 (Box 9, Folder 107)
  - Salvation Army: articles and photograph 1929-33 (Box 9, Folder 108)
  - Seventh Day Adventists: bookletundated (Box 9, Folder 109)
  - Society of Friends
    - General: articles and booklets 1929-59, undated (Box 9, Folder 110)
    - ARSC Women's NewsletterFebruary-December 1974 (Box 9, Folder 111)
    - Symposium on American Quaker Women (Guilford College, March, 1979): bibliographies, informational material, various Quaker women, statistics, essay, and articles1979 (Box 9, Folder 112)
  - Unitarian: articles and booklets 1922, undated (Box 9, Folder 113)
  - Universalists: articles 1923, 1930 (Box 9, Folder 114)
  - Unitarian/ Universalist
    - Clergy: book 1975 (Box 9, Folder 115)
    - U.U. Women's Federation
      - The Bridge (Periodical)March 1970-February 1971, Nov/Dec 1971 (Box 9, Folder 116)
      - Speak Out (Periodical)May 1971, Sept 1974, Dec 1974, Mar 1975, Nov 1975, Mar 1976 (Box 9, Folder 117)
  - Wicca: reportundated (Box 9, Folder 118)
- OVERSIZED MATERIAL
  - Scrapbook of historical data re: Christian Science to its founder, Mary Baker Eddy1935 (Box 10)
  - Faith and Feminism, Hellen Lakelly Hunt, 2004 (Box 10)
- BOOKS ON SHELF
  - Booth, Evangeline and Grace L. Hill. The War Romance of the Salvation Army 1919
  - Crook, Margaret Brackenbury. Women and Religion 1964
  - Driscoll, Annette. Literary Convert Women 1928
  - Howland, Susannah R. Early Quakerism 1885
  - Lollis, Lorraine. The Shape of Adam's Rib 1970
  - Rankin, Mary. Daughter of Affliction 1871
  - Royden, A. Maude. Blessed Joan of Arc 1918
  - Sergio, Lisa. Jesus and Woman: An exciting discovery of what he offered her 1975
  - Spencer, J. A., ed. The Women of Early Christianity 1851
  - Van Lennep, Mary E. Memoir of Mrs. Mary E. Van Lennep (missionary in Turkey)1848